Guide to the Irish Film Association Records AIA.017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
Irish Film Association Records
Bulk, 1991-1996
1986-1997
AIA.017
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive
0.75 linear feet in 2 manuscript boxes
The Irish Film Association, U.S.A. was founded in September 1991 by a group of Irish people living in New York who felt that the works of modern, independent Irish filmmakers, and the aspects of Irish culture these films depict, were not properly represented in America. The organization promoted these works that otherwise would have been impossible or difficult to see through screenings, lectures, the Scannan film festival, and other events. This collection documents the organization’s functions and activities. Materials include event flyers, memoranda, correspondence, newsletters, mailing lists, meeting minutes, newspaper articles, and publicity prints from various Irish films.
Irish Film Association, U.S.A..
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated in 2000. The accession number associated with this collection is 1997.047.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
The Irish Film Association, U.S.A. was founded in September 1991 by a group of Irish people living in New York who felt that the works of modern, independent Irish filmmakers, and the aspects of Irish culture these films depict, were not properly represented in America. The organization promoted these works that otherwise would have been impossible or difficult to see through screenings, lectures, the Scannan film festival, and other events. Officers for the Irish Film Association included President Mary Doran, Vice President Melissa Shaw-Smith, Treasurer Anne Gleeson, and Secretary Heather B. Thiermann.
Source:
Press release, circa 1992; Irish Film Association Records; AIA 017; Box 2; Folder 4; Archives of Irish America; Tamiment Library, New York University Libraries.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Separated Materials
Some personal and financial materials were removed from the collection and returned to the donor.
Scope and Content Note
This collection documents the functions and activities of the Irish Film Association, U.S.A, and its efforts to increase the visibility of modern, independent Irish film in America. Materials include event flyers, memoranda, correspondence, newsletters, mailing lists, meeting minutes, newspaper articles, and publicity prints from various Irish films. The collection also includes documents related to the planning of the organization’s film festival, Scannan.
Ireland |x In motion pictures.; Irish Americans |x Ethnic identity.; Irish Americans |x Societies, etc.; Motion Pictures |z Ireland
- Cine Gael Montreal, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Cinema Arts Centre (Huntington, New York), 1995 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Correspondence, 1995-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Cultural Relations Committee (Consulate General of Ireland), 1995-1996 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Films: The Cake, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Films: The Crying Game, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Films: Cullyhanna: Report of the Public Inquiry, Oct 2, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Films: Fragments of Isabella, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Films: Hush-A-Bye Baby, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Films: Lamb, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Films: Reefer and the Model, 1987-1989 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Irish Edition, Feb 1995 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- The Madame Macadam Travelling Theatre Playbill, Oct 1992 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Mailing Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Media Contact Lists, undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Meeting Minutes, Oct 30, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Museum of Television and Radio, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Newsletter, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Notebooks, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-2, Box 1, Folder 21-24)
- Press Releases, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Publicity, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Reservations, circa 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Scannan Festival, 1992-1996 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Technical Training, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- University College Dublin, Dec 1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Video Project Proposals, Feb 1991 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- "A Work in Progress on the Aran Islands," Deborah Meehan, Mar 1, 1996 (Box 2, Folder 10)